Finding Aid for David L. Littmann papers, 1964-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David L. Littmann papers
1964-2014
1970-2010
Littmann, David L.
0742 Aa 2; Ac
Chief Economist and Senior Vice President of Comerica Bank, author of the bank’s monthly business brochure, regular commentator on local and national radio and TV programs. The collection includes publications, speeches, and correspondence.
13.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
4 oversize folders
2.0 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by David Littmann (donor no. 9804 ) in November 2006. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
David L. Littmann was born in Rockford, Ill. He holds a B.A. from Antioch College, an M.S. degree from M.I.T., and received his M.A. degree in economics from the University of Michigan in 1967.
Mr. Littmann joined Comerica Bank in 1970 and retired in 2005 as Chief Economist and Senior Vice President. He was the author of the Bank's monthly business brochure, entitled "Business Briefs," and developed a variety of predictive indicators for the United States and regional economies. David Littmann authored several research articles on the causes of inflation which were published in Business Economics and wrote a monthly business column for The Detroiter. He is a frequent book reviewer and columnist for the Detroit News, Wall Street Journal, Investor's Business Daily, and others. Littmann is also a regular commentator in local and national television and radio. In 2005 columnist Susan Tompor of the Detroit Free Press called him the "most-quoted economic guru in Michigan."
Starting in 1990, Littmann served as President of The Heartland Institute in Michigan and is the Senior Economist for the Mackinac Center for Public Policy. He has served on the Governor's Council for Economic Advisors for Governor Engler, was named the top economic forecaster in the U.S. by the Wall Street Journal in July 1998, and is the recipient of the Lawrence R. Klein Award for Blue Chip Accuracy from 1999 to 2002. Mr. Littmann served as a trustee, treasurer, and vice president of the Bloomfield Hills School Board between 1982 and 1986.
Through writings and speeches, the David Littmann collection provides a look into the state of Michigan's economy, especially as it relates to tax policy and the automobile industry, from 1974 to 2014. The collection is divided into eight series: Biographical, Correspondence, Manuscripts, Publications, Press, Speeches, Audio Visual, and Publications/Press Additions.
Subjects:
Littmann, David L.; Economic forecasting--United States.; Economic forecasting--Michigan.; Economic forecasting--Michigan--Detroit.; Budget--United States.; Budget--Michigan.; Budget--Michigan--Detroit.; Fiscal policy--United States.; Fiscal policy--Michigan.; Taxation--United States.; Taxation--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Littmann, David L.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--21st century.; Federal government--United States--21st century--Speeches, addresses, etc.; Fiscal policy--United States--21st century--Speeches, addresses, etc.; Littmann, David L.; United States--Economic conditions--21st century--Speeches, addresses, etc.; United States--Politics and government--21st century--Speeches, addresses, etc.
Genre Terms:
Digital moving image formats.; Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Biographical, 1971-2006
  The Biographical series (1971-2006; 0.25 linear feet) contains items relating to the personal accomplishments of David L. Littmann, including his receipt of the Lawrence R. Klein Award for Blue Chip Accuracy and his meeting with President George W. Bush in 2003.
  - Annual Performance Review, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Bloomfield Hills Board Of Education, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Blue Chip Forecast Accuracy Award, 2003; 2004 (Box 1)
  - Governor's Council of Economic Advisors, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Mackinac Center in the Press, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Citizen Of The Year Award, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Photograph (headshot) (Box 1)
  - Photographic Slides (from speech) (Box 1)
  - Poster board tribute to DLL (Box 1)
  - Poster board tribute to DLL (Box 2)
    (continued)
  - Poster board tribute to DLL (Box 3)
  - Poster board tribute to DLL (Box 4)
  - Resume, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Retirement (Press), 2005; 2006 (Box 1)
  - Short Biographies, 1979; 1992; 1994; 2000 undated (Box 1)
  - Wall Street Journal Top Forecaster, 1998 (Box 1)
  - White House Visit With President George W. Bush, 2003 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1970-2006
  The Correspondence series (1970-2006; 4.75 linear feet) concerns Mr. Littmann's daily business interactions.
  - 1970-1980, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - 1981-1985, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1986-1989, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - 1989-1992, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - 1993-1996, 13 folders (Box 5)
  - (re: Promotion), 1998 (Box 5)
  - 1999-2006 (Box 5)
- Manuscripts, 1974-1992
  The Manuscript series (1974-1992; 0.25 feet) contains short articles, some of which are early drafts of published material.
  - 1974-1979 (Box 6)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 6)
  - 1991 (Box 6)
  - 1992 (Box 6)
  - Undated (Box 6)
- Press, 1964-2006
  The Press series (1964-2006; 1.25 feet) includes newspaper and magazine articles where David Littmann was quoted or mentioned. He is frequently used as an authoritative source concerning Michigan's economy. Mr. Littmann's expertise about the automotive industry is called upon in international publications from Germany,Finland, Japan and Brazil.
  - Interview Transcripts
    - WDIV-TV, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - CNBC, 2002 (Box 6)
    - 2003 (Box 6)
  - Magazines
    - 1972-2004, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Media Contact Logs, 1995-2000 (Box 6)
  - Newspapers
    - 1964-1989, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - 1990-2006, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
  - "Sunshine Economist" Scripts, WJR, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
  - Oversized Newspaper and Magazine Press (Folder 1)
- Publications, 1979-2005
  The Publications series (1979-2005; 3 feet) contains David Littmann's numerous publications for Comerica Bank and Manufacturers National Bank. Also included are Op-Ed pieces and book reviews, mostly from The Detroit News and The Wall Street Journal, typically pertaining to economic issues such as taxes and inflation. This series also includes some early drafts and editorial correspondence as well as reader correspondence.
  - Affiliated Bank
    - Economic Newsletter, Chicago, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - Business Economics (Journal of the NABE)
    - 1979 (Box 7)
    - 1980 (Box 7)
  - Comerica Bank
    - Automotive Newsletter, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Corporate Alliance, 1993-1997 (Box 7)
    - Economic Briefs, 1996-2005 (Box 7)
    - Economic Newsletter, California, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Economic Newsletter, Chicago, 1991-1995 (Box 7)
    - Economic Newsletter, Michigan, 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - Economic Newsletter, Texas, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Personal Trust, 1986-1993 (Box 7)
    - Spectrum, 1995-2005; 10 folders (Box 7)
  - Comerica Bank/Manufacturers National Bank, Business Briefs, 1972-1995; 23 volumes (Box 8)
  - Detroiter Magazine (with indices), 1979-2002; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Editorials, Book Reviews, Articles, Etc.
    - 1973-1999, 21 folders (Box 9)
    - 2001-2006, 6 folders (Box 10)
    - Undated (Box 10)
  - Manufacturers National Bank
    - Economic Newsletter, Detroit, 1984-1992 (Box 10)
    - Insight includes index, 1982-1992 (Box 10)
    - Interests, 1988-1990 (Box 10)
    - Trends, 1984-1988 (Box 10)
  - Masters Thesis, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Purchasing Management Association of Detroit
    - Press Releases, 1987-1992 (Box 10)
- Speeches, 1965-2006
  The Speeches series (1965-2006; 2 feet) has scripts of Mr. Littmann's frequent personal appearances for private and public organizations. Many speeches reflect Mr. Littmann's disdain for taxes and government over-spending.
  - 1965-1989, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - 1990-2000, 14 folders (Box 11)
  - 2001-2006, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - Undated (Box 12)
- Audio Visual
  The Audio Visual series (1993-2014; 1.5 feet and 2.0 GB) contains video and audio recordings featuring David Littman. This includes video cassettes of speeches about contemporary economic issues and television appearances as an interviewee and panelist; audio cassette recordings of two speeches; and digital video recordings downloaded from YouTube and Vimeo of speeches and interviews on economic and political issues.
  - Audio Cassettes
    - "The Economy and the Automobile Market," Speech, undated (Box 13)
    - "Is Our Unique Leadership Position Going To Waste," Speech, New Orleans, 1994 (Box 13)
  - VHS Videotapes
    - Automotive Insight Session, Speech, 2003 (Box 13)
    - Comcast Newsmakers Interview
      - 2002 (Box 13)
      - 2003 (Box 13)
      - Undated (Box 13)
    - Economic Club of Detroit Luncheon, Speech, December 11, 2000 (Box 13)
    - Law Talk Interview
      - 1995 (Box 13)
      - 1996 (Box 13)
    - Madonna College Magazine Interview, 1989 (Box 13)
    - McCuistion Program, Panelist, 2003 (Box 13)
    - One On One Interview
      - 1994 (Box 13)
      - 1997 (Box 13)
    - Straight Talk Interview (Presidential Town Meeting Reaction), 1993 (Box 13)
  - DVDs, 2 optical disks DVDs
    - "Eye on Oakland; Reality Check", March 9, 2007 (Box 13)
    - "Senior Matters; The Economy and Your Retirement", March 2008 (Box 13)
  - Digital Video Recordings
    - "Bankrupt: How Cronyism and Corruption Brought Down Detroit," documentary directed by Ben Howe, 2014; .ZIP file
    - Libertarian Party of Michigan, LibertyFest, David Littman address, November 14, 2009; .ZIP file
    - Mackinac Center for Public Policy, "Weathering the Storm: An Interview with David Littmann,", May 7, 2009; .ZIP file
    - Metro Detroit Freedom Coalition (MEDEFCO), David Littmann address, circa March 2010; .ZIP file
    - MiLocalBank.org, David Littman's responses to questions at the Community Bankers of Michigan Convention, 2012; .ZIP file
    - Rocky Raczkowski for Congress, David Littmann speech of support, 2010; .ZIP file
    - South East Michigan 9.12 Tea Party, David Littmann speech, May 7, 2013; .ZIP file
    - Spring Arbor University Thomas H. Cobb President's Leadership Speaker Series, David Littman keynote address, "Navigating the Next Economic Storm,", November 14, 2011; .ZIP file
- Publications/Press Additions, 1988-2010
  The Publications/Press Additions series (1988-; 0.5 feet) includes Littmann's graphology column as well as other writings received after the first accession of papers.
  - Graphology column, 2006-2008 (Box 14)
  - Press, 2004 undated (Box 14)
  - Publications
    - 1988-1993 (Box 14)
    - 2007 (Box 14)
    - 2008 (Box 14)
    - 2009 (Box 14)
    - 2010 (Box 14)